<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Edinburgh, 22. September, 1648. Whereas, many within this kingdom have joyned in armes for prosecuting of an unlawfull engagement against our neighbour nation of England, contrary to the Solemn League and Covenant, and treaties betwixt the kingdoms; the warnings and declarations of the commission of the General Assembly 1647. ...</title>
            <author>Scotland. Parliament. Committee of Estates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1355A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184021</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51617454</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51617454</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175361</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05271)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175361)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2730:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Edinburgh, 22. September, 1648. Whereas, many within this kingdom have joyned in armes for prosecuting of an unlawfull engagement against our neighbour nation of England, contrary to the Solemn League and Covenant, and treaties betwixt the kingdoms; the warnings and declarations of the commission of the General Assembly 1647. ...</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament. Committee of Estates.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler, Printer to the Kings most excellent Majestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from caption and first lines of text.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signed: Tho. Henderson.</note>
                  <note>A proclamation in two parts: one concerning the unlawfulness of breaking the peace with England; the other declaring that persons who are in arms against, or hostile towards, England should be barred from posts of high responsibility.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1649-1660 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:175361:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <opener>
               <dateline>Edinburgh, <date>22. September, 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas, many within this Kingdom have joyned in Armes for proſecuting of an unlawful Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt our neighbour Nation of <hi>England,</hi> contrary to the Solemn League and Covenant, and Treaties betwixt the Kingdoms; the Warnings and Declarations of the Commiſſion of the Generall Aſſembly 1647. And likew ſe againſt the unanimous proceedings and Declarations of the late Generall Aſſembly and their Commiſſioners: And whereas God hath evidently manifeſted his diſpleaſure and wrath againſt their ſinfull wayes and proceedings, in oppreſſing the wel-affected in this Kingdom, invading the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> by Routing and Defeating their Army there: And now ſome of their Army have returned to this Kingdom, and joyned with others their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociats to diſturb the peace thereof: By which their proceedings and actions, the work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Religion, hath been almoſt wholly overturned, the Libertie of the Subject very neer deſtroyed, authority weakened, the Perſon of the King put in hazard, the union betwixt the Kingdoms endeavoured to be broken, occaſion of quarrell given to our neighbour Nation, and this Kingdom brought to ſo ſad and deplorable condition, as (if the Lord in mercy prevent not) Famine and deſolation is like to be added to all our troubles and miſeries: Therefore to prevent the eminent dangers to Religion, and to the King, for ſetling the peace of this greatly diſtracted Kingdom. And to the end the affairs of this Kingdom may not be managed by ſuch perſons, as the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> do eſteem enemies for their concurrence in the late Engagement: The Committee of Eſtates conſiſting of ſuch perſons as were nominated to be on the Commiſſion of Parliament, and did diſ-aſſent in Parliament from, and Proteſt againſt the late unlawfull Engagement. Do declare that they are reſolved to Act and direct in the publict affairs by vertue of the Authority of that nomination of the Parliament, and their Legall Proteſtation in it: And that in Acting and Directing, they reſolve to proceed with the advice and conſent of ſuch Members of the late Parliament, as did concur with them in the ſaid Proteſtation, and do now concur in Armes in proſecuting of the ſame: As alſo with the advice and conſent of ſuch two Commiſſioners, and one Burgeſſe as ſhall be entruſted reſpect vely, by the Shires and Burghs joyning with us in Armes for the Covenant; and that they will not admit into their Counſells, or Committees, any perſons who have concurred in Armes, or Counſell for the late unlawfull Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or who have ſubſcribed the Bond, or ſworne, or ſubſcribed any Oath, or Declaration for proſecuting that Engagement. And further that they will admit none who have been aiding, or ſhall be aiding or aſſiſting to, or abetting and agenting for theſe who are now joyned in Armes with the Earl of <hi>Crawford,</hi> Earl of <hi>Glancairn,</hi> Earl of <hi>Lanerk,</hi> Lord <hi>Sinclair,</hi> Lord Regiſter, <hi>George Monre,</hi> and their adherents, nor any ſuch as have, or ſhall declare their judgement againſt this Cauſe and our proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in purſuance thereof: And we ordain theſe Preſents to be publiſhed: And alſo to be Printed that none pretend ignorance.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. Tho. Henderſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <opener>
               <dateline>Edinburgh, <date>22. September, 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Committee of Eſtates conſidering that the putting of the diſ affected and Malignant Perſons in places of truſt and power in the ſeverall Shires and Bu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghs of this Kingdom, hath been one of the greateſt Cauſes which hath brought all theſe evils upon this Kingdom: And for the reaſons contained in the former Act, do therefore finde it neceſſary to require: And do hereby Command and require the ſeverall Shires in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of their Commiſsioners to Parliament and Burghs in Election of their Commiſsioners to Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Magiſtrates and Counſell, that they make choice of none, but ſuch as have continued conſtant and faithfull in this Cauſe: And that they will not admit any to be in the former places of truſt, Commiſsions, Magiſtracie or Counſells who have concurred in Arms or Counſell for the late unlawfull Engagement, or who have ſubſcribed the Bond, or ſworne, or ſubſcribed any Oath or Declaration for proſecuting that Engagement. And further that they will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit none who have been aiding, or ſhall be aiding, or aſſiſting to, or abetting and agenting for theſe who are now joyned in Armes with the Earls of <hi>Crawford,</hi> Earl of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lenca<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rn,</hi> Earl of <hi>Lanerk,</hi> Lord <hi>Sinclair,</hi> Lord Regiſter, <hi>George Monro</hi> and their adherents, nor any ſuch as have, or ſhall declare then judgement againſt the Cauſe and our proceedings in purſuance thereof. And we ordain theſe preſents to be publiſhed at the Mercar Croſſe of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and other places needfull: And alſo to be Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that none pretend ignorance.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Mr. <hi>Tho: Henderſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Edinburgh, <hi>Printed by</hi> Evan Tyler, <hi>Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſtie,</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
